<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: php | Seventeen Past One]]></title>
  <link href="http://pfac.github.io/blog/categories/php/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pfac.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-25T14:01:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://pfac.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[pfac]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The prodigal son - Preface]]></title>
    <link href="http://pfac.github.io/blog/2014/04/25/the-prodigal-son-preface/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-25T13:23:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pfac.github.io/blog/2014/04/25/the-prodigal-son-preface</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--more-->


<p>Several years ago (god I'm old), just after I've finished high school, I plunged into the world of PHP. My previous experience was in classes using ASP (the old one), and I did not want to keep myself locked in the Microsoft world. I already had a great respect for open-source back then.</p>

<p>For more than a month, I lived, breathed and ate web. I improved my understanding of HTML, XML and XHTML. I practised CSS 2.1 to the point where I was having discussions in forums to understand why IE was so much different. I created my first website (nothing worth showing), with PHP controlling everything on the background. I even learned Javascript, not much, just enough so I would never come to "fear" it.</p>

<p>Using PHP I implemented my own router, authentication mechanism, template language, and I didn't even know I was doing so. I <em>spaghetti-ed</em> my way in a webapp, and faced the overwhelming feeling of losing the control over your own creation.</p>

<p>After that summer, I left PHP. I only dealt with it once more, in my third year of college, for an assignment where we had to create a simple webapp to manage a database (basically just CRUD). By that time, I had already spent too much time away from web development (I was more into games), and whenever the subject surfaced in a conversation my antennas where already tuned to Ruby on Rails.</p>

<p>In the last year and a half, I got started with Rails, I got to play with Angular, and I ended up getting a job working with Java EE right after I finished my master's.</p>

<p>Now the prodigal son returns. A friend has just approached me with a challenge, a simple webapp, but it will have to be done in PHP. My <em>spaghetti</em> days are long gone, but several questions now arise:</p>

<ul>
<li>Am I able to relearn a language that I've come to consider so inferior?</li>
<li>Can I translate my (short) Rails knowledge to Laravel, Symfony or Yii?</li>
<li>Do I even need a framework, or can I just adapt Drupal like so many have before?</li>
</ul>


<p>And like everything in life, the time to make a decision is very limited...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
